## PEDRO HESPANHOL

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Ph.D student in Industrial Engineering and Operations Research at UC Berkeley. Previous work experience in software development, data science and optimization algorithms.

Current research interests are: control-based optimization, machine learning, and learning-based mechanism design. Also interested in all aspects of computational optimization, from modeling techniques to practical

- EDUCATION

Ph.D.: Industrial Engineering and Operations Research, 08/2015 - Current

University Of California, Berkeley - Berkeley

- MS in Industrial Engineering and Operation Research (08/2015-08/2016)
- 3.94/4.0 GPA

implementations.

- Advisor: Professor Anil Aswani
- Minors: Statistics and Economics

Relevant research (coursework) experience in the following areas:

- Optimization Theory and Optimal Control (Math Programming I & II / Computational Optimization / Graph Algorithms and Network Flows / Predictive Control / Learning and Optimization / Applied Dynamic Programming)
- Statistical Learning and Deep Learning (Statistical Learning Theory / Deep Time-Series Learning)
- Game Theory and Mechanism Design (Microeconomics and Game Theory / Mechanism Design and Agency Theory)
- Financial Engineering and Stochastic Processes (Financial Engineering I & II / Stochastic Processes I & II)

Bachelor of Science: Industrial Engineering, 01/2010-12/2014

Pontifical Catholic University of Rio de Janeiro - Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

- Minor in Risk Analysis and Statistics
- 9.6/ 10.0 GPA

#### - Publications

#### Surrogate Optimal Control for Strategic Multi-Agent Systems

Pedro Hespanhol and Anil Aswani

Submitted to 2019 Conference on Decision and Control (CDC)

## Statistical Consistency in Switching System Identification

Pedro Hespanhol and Anil Aswani

Submitted to 2019 Conference on Decision and Control (CDC)

# Adjoint-based SQP Method with Block-wise quasi-Newton Jacobian Updates for Nonlinear Optimal Control

Pedro Hespanhol and Rien Quirynen

Submitted to Optimization Methods and Software Journal

#### Finite-Time Dynamic Watermarking for General LTI Systems with Switching

Pedro Hespanhol, Matthew Porter, Ramanarayan Vasudevan, Anil Aswani -

On ArXiv. To be submitted to IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control Journal

#### A Structure Exploiting Branch-and-Bound Algorithm for Mixed-Integer Model Predictive Control

Pedro Hespanhol, Rien Quirynen, Stefano Di Cairano

Accepted. To appear in the 2019 European Control Conference (ECC)

#### **Statistical Watermarking for Networked Control Systems**

Pedro Hespanhol, Matthew Porter, Ramanarayan Vasudevan, Anil Aswani - In the Proceedings of 2018 Annual American Control Conference (ACC), pp. 5467-5472. IEEE, 2018

#### **Dynamic Watermarking for General LTI Systems**

Pedro Hespanhol, Matthew Porter, Ramanarayan Vasudevan, Anil Aswani

In the Proceedings of Decision and Control (CDC), 2017 IEEE 56th Annual Conference on (pp. 1834-1839). IEEE

## Quasi-Newton Jacobian and Hessian Updates for Pseudospectral based NMPC

Pedro Hespanhol and Rien Quirynen

In the Proceedings of 2018 International Federation of Automatic Control (IFAC). IFAC-PapersOnLine, 51(20), 22-27.

# A Real-Time Iteration Scheme with Quasi-Newton Jacobian Updates for Nonlinear Model Predictive Control

Pedro Hespanhol and Rien Ouirynen

In the Proceedings of 2018 Annual European Control Conference (ECC). IEEE, 2018

#### Family-Personalized Dietary Planning with Temporal Dynamics

Pedro Hespanhol and Anil Aswani

In the Proceedings of 2018 Annual American Control Conference (ACC) (pp. 2163-2169). IEEE.

#### Simulation and Real-World Evaluation of Attack Detection Schemes

Porter, Matthew, Arnav Joshi, Pedro Hespanhol, Anil Aswani, Matthew Johnson-Roberson, and Ram Vasudevan *Accepted. To appear in the 2019 American Control Conference (ACC)* 

#### Impact of Occupancy Modeling and Horizon Length on HVAC Controller Efficiency

Christian Rabbi Garaza, Pedro Hespanhol, Yonatan Mintz, Jhoanna Rhodette Pedrasa, and Anil Aswani - In the Proceedings of 2018 Annual European Control Conference (ECC). IEEE, 2018

## Work History

#### **Research Intern**, 05/2018 to 08/2018

#### Mitsubishi Electric Research Laboratories (MERL) – Cambridge, MA

- Research on mixed-integer optimization algorithms. Developed efficient mixed integer software for fast online optimal control problems, focusing on implementation in embedded platforms.
- Developed algorithm in C and evaluated it's performance on realistic optimal control problems, beating state-of-art solvers/methods across several different problems.

#### **Research Intern**, 06/2017 to 09/2017

#### Mitsubishi Electric Research Laboratories (MERL) – Cambridge, MA

- Worked on research of efficient optimization algorithms tailored to solve non-linear optimal control problems, with emphasis on computational performance and solution tractability.
- Worked on implementation in C/C++ of such algorithms in embedded platforms, focusing on rigorously analyzing computation times and memory usage of the developed methods.

#### Graduate Student Instructor, 01/2017 to Current

## UC Berkeley – Berkeley

- Graduate Student Instructor for IEOR 265 Learning and Optimization. A graduate-level course which covers Model Predictive Control and high-dimensional statistics with applications in control and machine learning.
- Graduate Student Instructor for IEOR 262A Math Programming I. A graduate-level course which covers linear and nonlinear optimization theory and algorithms.
- Graduate Student Instructor for IEOR 165 Engineering Statistics, Quality Control, and Forecasting. A senior undergraduate-level course which covers classical statistical and modern machine learning techniques applied to several industrial applications.
- Graduate Student Instructor for IEOR 151 Service Design and Operation Analysis. A senior undergraduate-level course which covers the analysis and modelling of service-based systems.

#### Analyst, 08/2014 to 08/2015

## PSR - Energy Consulting and Analytics - Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

- Worked in the development team (SDDP software): Extensive use of C/C++ and high-level mathematical modelling languages and statistical tools to improve software performance, decrease run-time, and solution output.
- Programmed the optimization algorithm for HERA software: HERA is a geographical and financial analysis software to evaluate the construction of hydro power-plants. HERA team won ENGIE Brazil Innovation Prize in 2015.
- Developed mathematical models and algorithms to support decision making in: energy trading, portfolio optimization, operation planning and capacity expansion in power systems.

## Analyst (Internship program), 01/2012 to 07/2013

NexO – Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

- Worked in development team: Implemented a mathematical algorithm to optimally operate oil refineries. Work done together with CENPES (Petrobras' Research Center).
- Developed of a graphical interface to show the refineries products flows.

## Presentations and Invited Talks -

## **Statistical Watermarking for Networked Control Systems**

Annual American Control Conference, Milwaukee, USA, June 27-29, 2018.

#### **Newton Jacobian Updates for Nonlinear Model Predictive Control**

Annual European Control Conference, Lymassol, Cyprus, June 12-15 2018.

## **Family-Personalized Dietary Planning with Temporal Dynamics**

Annual American Control Conference, Milwaukee, USA, June 27-29, 2018.

#### **Dynamic Watermarking for General LTI Systems**

56th IEEE Conference on Decision and Control, Melbourne, Australia, December 12-15, 2017.

## Deterministic Approximation Algorithm For Population-Scale Personal Dietary Management

INFORMS Computing Society Conference, Austin, TX, 2017.

## Approximation Algorithms For Population-scale Personal Dietary Management

INFORMS Annual Meeting, Nashville, TN, 2016.

## Honors and Awards

**ENGIE Brazil Innovation Prize** - granted by ENGIE Group for the development of the HERA software. **PUC's Academic Performance Premium** - granted by Pontifical Catholic University of Rio de Janeiro. **Medal Graça Couto** - granted by the Military School of Rio de Janeiro.

**Medal Thomaz Coelho** - granted by the Military School of Rio de Janeiro.

## SKILLS

- Mathematical Programming: Xpress, Gurobi, CPLEX, GAMS, AMPL
- **Programming Languages:** C/C++ , Python, R, Matlab
- Machine Learning & Big Data: TensorFlow, Pandas, Keras
- Software\Algorithm Development

- Statistical and Risk Analysis
- **Soft Skills:** Communicative team member. Proactive leader. Problem-solving attitude.
- Languages: English, Portuguese, Spanish
- Others: VBA, @Risk, Eviews, MS Office

## VOLUNTEER WORK

#### Associação Paulo Cesar

• Worked with a group of students to recover and repair computers for children in the community of Morro do Adeus in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.